<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>homelab | Remotely Curious</title>
    <link>https://www.remotelycurious.net/tag/homelab/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.remotelycurious.net/tag/homelab/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>homelab</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 11:47:58 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.remotelycurious.net/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>homelab</title>
      <link>https://www.remotelycurious.net/tag/homelab/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building an Active Directory lab with Proxmox</title>
      <link>https://www.remotelycurious.net/post/activelab/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Jul 2021 11:47:58 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.remotelycurious.net/post/activelab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last couple of weeks, I decided that it would be good to learn a little something about Windows administration. The phrase &amp;ldquo;active directory&amp;rdquo; is something that I&amp;rsquo;ve often heard popping up in discussions about Windows security in the context of both offensive and defensive activity. Since 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ww2.frost.com/frost-perspectives/active-directory-holds-the-keys-to-your-kingdom-but-is-it-secure/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the vast majority of Fortune 500 companies&lt;/a&gt; make use of Active Directory in their corporate networks, perhaps it&amp;rsquo;s no small wonder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see what all the fuss is about (and maybe learn a thing or two), I built a virtualized Active Directory lab. As with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/post/homelab&#34;&gt;my previous homelab writeup&lt;/a&gt;, I thought it would be good to write this up to consolidate all the loose bits of information that I picked up along the way. For the initial domain controller installation, I took some hints from The Cyber Mentor&amp;rsquo;s guide for 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xftEuVQ7kY0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;building an AD hacking lab&lt;/a&gt;, as well as the documentation for 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://pve.proxmox.com/wiki/Main_Page&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Proxmox&lt;/a&gt; for advice on setting up Windows VMs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#installation&#34;&gt;Installation&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#domain-controller&#34;&gt;Domain controller&lt;/a&gt;
          &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#installing-windows-server&#34;&gt;Installing Windows Server&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#configuring-the-network&#34;&gt;Configuring the network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#promotion-to-domain-controller&#34;&gt;Promotion to domain controller&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#workstations&#34;&gt;Workstations&lt;/a&gt;
          &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#installing-windows-enterprise&#34;&gt;Installing Windows Enterprise&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#configuring-the-network-1&#34;&gt;Configuring the network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#join-workstation-to-domain&#34;&gt;Join workstation to domain&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#configuration&#34;&gt;Configuration&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#add-an-active-directory-user&#34;&gt;Add an active directory user&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#configure-remote-management&#34;&gt;Configure remote management&lt;/a&gt;
          &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My general motive is to learn more about the importance of Active Directory in securing a Windows network. Aside from this, I have some specific plans for how I will put this AD lab to use, which I talk about briefly at the end of the writeup. Most of these plans involve learning something that I have never used or seen in action (PowerShell, group policies, Windows events), so this should be fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since most of my immediate goals have something to do with Windows administration, I will be building a Windows &amp;ldquo;corporate network&amp;rdquo;, consisting of one Active Directory (AD) domain controller and a fleet of two Windows workstations. In a future project, these will eventually be configured to push event logs to a fourth machine, which will be responsible for event querying and log analysis. All of these machines will be implemented as Proxmox VMs that are connected to the same (virtual) network segment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To realize this tiny network, I could configure the workstation VMs individually, but setting up an AD domain will allow me to manage the workstations from the domain controller using group policies and PowerShell remote sessions. Individual VM configuration can therefore be limited to the initial OS/driver installation and static IP assignment. I like to think that this approach is scalable and bears some resemblance to how actual sysadmins carry out (a very small subset of) their duties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Full disclosure: I have never managed an enterprise network. Hopefully that last claim isn&amp;rsquo;t too offensive!
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this project, I&amp;rsquo;ll be recruiting my trusty 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://protectli.com/product/fw6b/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Protectli FW6B&lt;/a&gt;, which has been set up as a Proxmox hypervisor (you can find the corresponding writeup 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/post/homelab&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). This time around, I loaded it with 32 GiB of RAM to better handle the burden of running all these VMs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;installation&#34;&gt;Installation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Windows network consists of one domain controller (Windows Server 2019) and two workstations (Windows 10 Pro). Proxmox&amp;rsquo;s documentation recommends a specific set of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://pve.proxmox.com/wiki/Windows_VirtIO_Drivers&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;drivers for Windows VMs&lt;/a&gt; that do not come with the OS but promise to enhance device performance. These VirtIO drivers will be loaded during Windows&#39; installation using an extra virtualized CD/DVD reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following disk images will be used:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;17763.737.190906-2324.rs5_release_svc_refresh_SERVER_EVAL_x64FRE_en-us_1.iso&lt;/code&gt; (Windows 2019 Server)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;19043.928.210409-1212.21h1_release_svc_refresh_CLIENTENTERPRISEEVAL_OEMRET_x64FRE_en-us.iso&lt;/code&gt; (Windows 10 Enterprise)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;virtio-win-0.1.190.iso&lt;/code&gt; (VirtIO drivers)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;domain-controller&#34;&gt;Domain controller&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our setup will feature a &lt;em&gt;domain&lt;/em&gt;, a network of computers that is managed by a &lt;em&gt;domain controller&lt;/em&gt; (DC). Of its many responsibilities, the DC is tasked with making sure that all configured application and security policies are respected by all devices on the network. Among other things, we will use the DC to create domain user accounts that allow users to access the domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what DOMCON, the domain controller VM looks like under Proxmox:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 CPU core, 4 GiB RAM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;32 GiB VirtIO SCSI HDD (write-back, discard)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VirtIO NIC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2x DVD drives (Windows Server 2019; VirtIO driver package)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Remember that the Windows setup process won&amp;rsquo;t recognize the VirtIO devices, so make sure that the second DVD drive (e.g., &lt;code&gt;ide3&lt;/code&gt;) is loaded with the VirtIO ISO before powering it on. You should also ensure that this DVD drive has a higher device number than that of the installation media (e.g., 2 in &lt;code&gt;ide2&lt;/code&gt;), such that the VM attempts to boot off the Windows ISO first.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s boot up the VM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;installing-windows-server&#34;&gt;Installing Windows Server&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After clicking Install at the first installer prompt, you will be asked to select the OS to install. We are going to opt for Windows Server 2019 &lt;strong&gt;Standard Evaluation (Desktop Experience)&lt;/strong&gt; to get a graphical interface. There will be another prompt after you agree to the standard terms of use, asking about the type of installation. Select &lt;strong&gt;Custom: Install Windows only&lt;/strong&gt; to proceed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if you&amp;rsquo;ve gone with the configuration listed above, you won&amp;rsquo;t find any available drives to choose in this next screen. This is because Windows doesn&amp;rsquo;t recognize the SCSI disk drive, as expected. To install the drivers, click &lt;strong&gt;Load driver&lt;/strong&gt; and browse to &lt;code&gt;E:\vioscsi\2k19\amd64&lt;/code&gt;, which will yield the Red Hat VirtIO SCSI pass-through controller driver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After loading the driver, we&amp;rsquo;re ready for some partitioning. Select the newly-visible drive, click &lt;strong&gt;New&lt;/strong&gt;, and allocate the entire drive for the partition to get the screen below.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-1b-disk-partitions-shown-after-installing-the-virtio-scsi-drivers&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/partitions.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 1&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. Disk partitions, shown after installing the VirtIO SCSI drivers.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/partitions.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 1&lt;/b&gt;. Disk partitions, shown after installing the VirtIO SCSI drivers.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the second partition selected, click &lt;strong&gt;Next&lt;/strong&gt; and the installation will proceed. Eventually, the system will reboot and you will be asked to supply a password for the local Administrator account. After this, you can unlock the login screen with Ctrl-Alt-Delete and log in with those same credentials.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-2b-you-can-send-ctrl-alt-del-using-the-three-keys-button-in-the-proxmox-web-interface-sidebar&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/ctrl-alt-del.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 2&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. You can send Ctrl-Alt-Del using the &amp;amp;ldquo;three keys&amp;amp;rdquo; button in the Proxmox web interface sidebar.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/ctrl-alt-del.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 2&lt;/b&gt;. You can send Ctrl-Alt-Del using the &amp;ldquo;three keys&amp;rdquo; button in the Proxmox web interface sidebar.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;configuring-the-network&#34;&gt;Configuring the network&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first order of business is to establish network connectivity. This means we need to use the VirtIO disk image once more, since our NIC is also a VirtIO device. Enter Device Manager, find the &lt;em&gt;Ethernet Controller&lt;/em&gt; and click &lt;strong&gt;Update driver&lt;/strong&gt; (Fig. 3). Searching the &lt;code&gt;E:\NetKVM\2k19\amd64&lt;/code&gt; folder will yield the Red Hat VirtIO Ethernet Adapter driver.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-3b-updating-the-nic-driver-in-device-manager&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/device-manager.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 3&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. Updating the NIC driver in Device Manager.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/device-manager.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 3&lt;/b&gt;. Updating the NIC driver in Device Manager.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You will now get a prompt asking whether to allow network discovery. It&amp;rsquo;s a home network, so this is fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will now assign this machine with a static IP address. Under Network Connections, access the Properties of the Ethernet adapter and bring up the TCP/IPv4 properties (Fig. 4). Here, the default gateway is pointing to my home router.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-4b-setting-the-ip-address-and-default-gateway-for-the-dc&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/tcp-ip.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 4&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. Setting the IP address and default gateway for the DC.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/tcp-ip.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 4&lt;/b&gt;. Setting the IP address and default gateway for the DC.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After changing the computer name to DOMCON (e.g., right-click This PC &amp;raquo; Properties &amp;raquo; Change settings &amp;raquo; &lt;strong&gt;Change&lt;/strong&gt;), let the VM reboot and log back in. We are now ready to prepare our server to become a domain controller.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;promotion-to-domain-controller&#34;&gt;Promotion to domain controller&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are going to promote DOMCON to become the DC for our prospective Windows domain. This requires the installation of the AD Domain Services role, which can be initiated by using the Server Manager window (Fig. 5). Click Manage &amp;raquo; &lt;strong&gt;Add Roles and Features&lt;/strong&gt; to bring up a wizard and go through it as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Installation Type: &lt;em&gt;Role-based or feature-based installation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Server Selection: &lt;em&gt;DOMCON&lt;/em&gt; at 192.168.0.11&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Server Roles: Check &lt;em&gt;Active Directory Domain Services&lt;/em&gt; (click &lt;strong&gt;Add Features&lt;/strong&gt; to add the required services/features when prompted)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click through to the end and click &lt;strong&gt;Install&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-5b-using-the-server-manager-to-add-roles-and-additional-functionality&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/server-manager.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 5&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. Using the Server Manager to add roles and additional functionality.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/server-manager.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 5&lt;/b&gt;. Using the Server Manager to add roles and additional functionality.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After installation, we are shown a summary of what was installed, as well as a little line of text offering the option to promote the server to a domain controller (Fig. 6). Lovely.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-6b-choosing-to-promote-the-domain-controller&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/dc-promo.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 6&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. Choosing to promote the domain controller.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/dc-promo.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 6&lt;/b&gt;. Choosing to promote the domain controller.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clicking this brings us to another wizard. At the Deployment Configuration page, select &lt;strong&gt;Add a new forest&lt;/strong&gt; and enter the root domain name. We are running a test lab so our choice of domain name here doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter. I will call mine &lt;em&gt;labs.remotelycurious.net&lt;/em&gt;. Go through the rest of the wizard and click &lt;strong&gt;Install&lt;/strong&gt; at the Prerequisites Check page. Reboot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After reaching the Windows login, notice that the &lt;code&gt;Administrator&lt;/code&gt; account becomes prefixed with &lt;code&gt;LABS&lt;/code&gt;, indicating the presence of the newly-created domain. You will also find that the DC&amp;rsquo;s preferred DNS server is now configured as itself, i.e., 127.0.0.1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;workstations&#34;&gt;Workstations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to cook up some clients. The installation and initial configuration of these VMs will be very familiar, having just set up Windows Server for the domain controller. Each client VM will have these specs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 CPU core, 2 GiB RAM&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;32 GiB VirtIO SCSI HDD (write-back, discard)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;VirtIO NIC&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2x DVD drives (Windows 10 Enterprise; VirtIO driver package)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steps for setting up WINCLIENT-1 (192.168.0.21/24) are outlined below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;installing-windows-enterprise&#34;&gt;Installing Windows Enterprise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After starting the Windows installation, we click through and arrive at the install location page, as we did in Figure 1. Click &lt;strong&gt;Load driver&lt;/strong&gt; and browse to &lt;code&gt;E:\vioscsi\w10\amd64&lt;/code&gt; to install the Red Hat VirtIO SCSI pass-through controller driver for Windows 10. Allocate the partitions as desired and continue with the installation. Reboot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once Windows boots, you will be asked to enter the credentials and security questions of a local user (so long as you aren&amp;rsquo;t connected to the internet). Go ahead and set these, click through some more prompts, and wait for Windows to finish setting up your local account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;configuring-the-network-1&#34;&gt;Configuring the network&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The VirtIO network adapter needs a driver. Use Device Manager to update the driver using the RedHat one located at &lt;code&gt;E:\NetKVM\w10\amd64&lt;/code&gt;. After the driver update, accept the offer to enable network discovery and change the computer name to WINCLIENT-1. Reboot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To join the domain, the workstations need to be placed on the same subnet as the domain controller. As was done for the server, we will install the NIC driver (Fig. 3) and configure the adapter&amp;rsquo;s TCP/IP settings:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;IP address: 192.168.0.21/24&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gateway: 192.168.0.1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;DNS: 192.168.0.11&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;join-workstation-to-domain&#34;&gt;Join workstation to domain&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click Start, type &amp;lsquo;domain&amp;rsquo; and click &lt;strong&gt;Access work or school&lt;/strong&gt;. After clicking &lt;strong&gt;Connect&lt;/strong&gt;, you will find the option to &lt;em&gt;Join this device to a local Active Directory domain&lt;/em&gt; below. Go ahead and enter &lt;code&gt;labs&lt;/code&gt; to access a login prompt, and enter the labs\Administrator credentials to make the connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After restarting, the VM will be joined to the domain. Repeat the process for WINCLIENT-2 and a different IP and you will have yourself a &amp;ldquo;fleet&amp;rdquo; of two computers that can be centrally managed by the domain controller.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-7b-check-out-the-fleet&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/resolve-dnsnames.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 7&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. Check out the fleet!&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/resolve-dnsnames.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 7&lt;/b&gt;. Check out the fleet!
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;configuration&#34;&gt;Configuration&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that the workstations have been linked up to the domain, we&amp;rsquo;re ready for some configuration. An enterprise needs users, so we will need at least one of those. I&amp;rsquo;ve also decided that it will be useful to have the option of managing the workstations remotely through PowerShell sessions, as mentioned earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;add-an-active-directory-user&#34;&gt;Add an active directory user&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;User accounts can be created using the Active Directory Users and Computers app, but it is relatively easy to do this through PowerShell. Open up a shell as Administrator and run the command below to create a new AD user account for Steven Strange (mind the ticks that let the command span multiple lines).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;New-ADUser `
  -Name &amp;quot;Steven Strange&amp;quot; -GivenName &amp;quot;Steven&amp;quot; -Surname &amp;quot;Strange&amp;quot; `
  -SamAccountName &amp;quot;sstrange&amp;quot; `
  -ChangePasswordAtLogon $False `
  -AccountPassword $(ConvertTo-SecureString &amp;quot;Letmein123!&amp;quot; -AsPlainText -Force) `
  -PassThru | Enable-ADAccount
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few things to note here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;code&gt;SamAccountName&lt;/code&gt; parameter is mandatory; all others are optional,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the account password is set using an encrypted string object (&lt;code&gt;System.Security.SecureString&lt;/code&gt;), evaluated using the &lt;code&gt;$(...)&lt;/code&gt; subexpression,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &lt;code&gt;PassThru&lt;/code&gt; option tells the &lt;code&gt;New-ADUser&lt;/code&gt; command to return the new AD user object, which we then pipe to &lt;code&gt;Enable-ADAccount&lt;/code&gt; to save us an extra step (new accounts are disabled by default).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After verifying that we can log in as Steven Strange on one of the client VMs, we can go ahead and set up remote management for the fleet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;configure-remote-management&#34;&gt;Configure remote management&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this stage is to enable Windows Remote Management (WinRM) throughout the domain. We can do this through the application of three different policies within the Group Policy Management app. Navigate to Domains &amp;raquo; labs.remotelycurious.net &amp;raquo; Group Policy Objects &amp;raquo; Default Domain Policy, right-click and click &lt;strong&gt;Edit&lt;/strong&gt; to bring up the Group Policy Management Editor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Note to self: learn how to do this through PowerShell. Way too much clicking.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;1-enable-remote-management-winrm&#34;&gt;1. Enable Remote Management (WinRM)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Find &lt;em&gt;Windows Remote Management&lt;/em&gt; under Computer Configuration &amp;raquo; Policies &amp;raquo; Windows Settings &amp;raquo; Security Settings &amp;raquo; System Services, right-click and hit &lt;strong&gt;Properties&lt;/strong&gt;. Check &lt;em&gt;Define this policy setting&lt;/em&gt; and select the &lt;em&gt;Automatic&lt;/em&gt; service startup mode before clicking &lt;strong&gt;OK&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-8b-winrm-has-just-been-enabled&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/enable-winrm.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 8&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. WinRM has just been enabled.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/enable-winrm.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 8&lt;/b&gt;. WinRM has just been enabled.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;2-allow-remote-management-through-winrm&#34;&gt;2. Allow remote management through WinRM&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After enabling the service, the next step is to actually allow it to operate. Find the &lt;em&gt;Allow remote server management through WinRM&lt;/em&gt; setting under Computer Configuration &amp;raquo; Policies &amp;raquo; Administrative Templates &amp;raquo; Windows Components &amp;raquo; Windows Remote Management &amp;raquo; WinRM Service, right-click and choose &lt;strong&gt;Edit&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we can choose which IPs will be allowed to establish a remote connection. After enabling the setting, fill in the IPv4 field appropriately and click &lt;strong&gt;OK&lt;/strong&gt;. In my case, the Windows network spans from 192.168.0.11 to 192.168.0.22, and I want to be able to remote from any PC to any other one, just for fun.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-9b-allowing-winrm-connections-from-any-pc-in-the-windows-network&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/allow-winrm.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 9&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. Allowing WinRM connections from any PC in the Windows network.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/allow-winrm.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 9&lt;/b&gt;. Allowing WinRM connections from any PC in the Windows network.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;3-add-winrm-firewall-exception&#34;&gt;3. Add WinRM firewall exception&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve hit the last stretch, in which we have to allow the remote connection through the firewall. This is done by making an inbound port exception for the WinRM service, which runs on port 5985. Dig up the &lt;em&gt;Define inbound port exceptions&lt;/em&gt; setting under Computer Configuration &amp;raquo; Policies &amp;raquo; Administrative Templates &amp;raquo; Network &amp;raquo; Network Connections &amp;raquo; Windows Defender Firewall &amp;raquo; Domain Profile, right-click and choose &lt;strong&gt;Edit&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After clicking &lt;strong&gt;Enabled&lt;/strong&gt;, click &lt;strong&gt;Show&lt;/strong&gt; under &lt;em&gt;Define port exceptions&lt;/em&gt;. Each exception is specified in the format &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;port&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;transport&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;scope&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;status&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;, where&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;transport&lt;/code&gt; is either TCP or UDP,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;scope&lt;/code&gt; indicates the originating networks that are allowed through the firewall,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;status&lt;/code&gt; is either &amp;lsquo;enabled&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;disabled&amp;rsquo;, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;name&lt;/code&gt; can hold a short description of the rule.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will enter &lt;code&gt;5985:TCP:localsubnet:enabled:WinRM&lt;/code&gt; to allow local TCP connections through port 5985. That should do it, but the proof is in the pudding. Let&amp;rsquo;s try to connect to WINCLIENT-2 from the domain controller. Does it work?&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-10b-were-in&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/enter-pssession.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 10&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. &amp;amp;ldquo;We&amp;amp;rsquo;re in&amp;amp;rdquo;.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/activelab/enter-pssession.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 10&lt;/b&gt;. &amp;ldquo;We&amp;rsquo;re in&amp;rdquo;.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have ourselves a miniature enterprise Windows network, complete with a domain controller and remote management capabilities. There are certainly ways I can make it better (maybe configure WinRM to use TLS?) but it will do the job for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m really keen to see if I can use this network as a platform for threat detection. Right now, my thinking is to set up event forwarding such that a selection of Windows events from the AD network is shipped to an Elastic Stack SIEM for log analysis. The idea would be to generate test threats (maybe with Atomic Red Team) and see if I can detect any malicious activity using Elasticsearch queries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, that&amp;rsquo;s a post for another day.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building a homelab with Proxmox</title>
      <link>https://www.remotelycurious.net/post/homelab/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 23:13:08 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.remotelycurious.net/post/homelab/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;It turns out that the journey to setting up a homelab is filled with trapdoors and snake pits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This writeup is largely for documentation purposes &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s written as a note to my future self who might look to recreate this setup and wonder why certain design decisions were made. My goal is to avoid having to rediscover all of the little hazards that can (and did) result in hours of frustration. That said, my hope is that other people with similar goals can learn from my experience and save themselves from navigating seas of browser tabs in search of enlightenment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the time my homelab took shape, I had made use of all sorts of resources on the topic. One of the best belongs to Dan Ford, whose excellent 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dlford.io/tag/how-to-home-lab-series/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;homelab writeup series&lt;/a&gt; really helped me to get started. The documentation for 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://pve.proxmox.com/wiki/Main_Page&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Proxmox&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.netgate.com/pfsense/en/latest/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;pfSense&lt;/a&gt; was also useful. Aside from these, there were also many valuable snippets of information, forum posts and docpages scattered throughout the internet, which have been cited where appropriate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#hardware&#34;&gt;Hardware&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#hypervisor&#34;&gt;Hypervisor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#network&#34;&gt;Network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#installation&#34;&gt;Installation&lt;/a&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#installing-proxmox&#34;&gt;Installing Proxmox&lt;/a&gt;
          &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#file-system&#34;&gt;File system&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#network-configuration&#34;&gt;Network configuration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#configuring-proxmox&#34;&gt;Configuring Proxmox&lt;/a&gt;
          &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#enabling-software-updates&#34;&gt;Enabling software updates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#uploading-iso-images&#34;&gt;Uploading ISO images&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#configuring-the-virtual-network&#34;&gt;Configuring the virtual network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#installing-pfsense&#34;&gt;Installing pfSense&lt;/a&gt;
          &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#configuring-pfsense&#34;&gt;Configuring pfSense&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#creating-the-internal-network&#34;&gt;Creating the internal network&lt;/a&gt;
          &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#restricting-access&#34;&gt;Restricting access&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;objectives&#34;&gt;Objectives&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a lot of reasons you might want to build a homelab. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/homelab/comments/4mc7sf/why_build_a_homelab_some_thoughts_for_beginners/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Many of them&lt;/a&gt; have to do with learning something. My short-term goal is to learn system administration (things like configuring firewalls and networks, managing security policy, etc) but eventually I want to learn more about network intrusion detection. I&amp;rsquo;d be curious to see if I could break into my own network &amp;ndash; and what that would look like from the perspective of a sysadmin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A homelab can take many forms, from an array of physical computers mounted on racks, to a book-sized unit hosting a virtualized computer network. In this section I discuss the major constraints and design decisions that guided my approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hardware&#34;&gt;Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I like quiet and despise both heat and clutter, the first major constraint was that this homelab needed to be virtual. This means the homelab is going to be implemented by a bare-metal hypervisor&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, on a host computer with a low noise, power, and physical profile. In the end I went with the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://protectli.com/product/fw6b/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Protectli FW6B&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s a silent, well-built unit that comes with a dual-core i3-7100U and 6x Intel Gigabit NICs. I opted to load it with 2x8 GiB of DDR4 RAM and 480 GiB of mSATA storage. This is definitely overkill for a bunch of lightweight VMs, but I&amp;rsquo;ll be putting this little box to good use in future projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Whatever you do, make sure that your host CPU supports virtualization!
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    According to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/homelab/comments/7at38f/1gig_pcie_nic_recommendations/&#34;&gt;people who know better&lt;/a&gt;, Intel NICs seem to better support virtualization, compared with those from other manufacturers.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;hypervisor&#34;&gt;Hypervisor&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a couple hours of internet research, I decided to run with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.proxmox.com/en/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Proxmox&lt;/a&gt; as my hypervisor. People also seem to be pretty happy with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vmware.com/products/esxi-and-esx.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ESXi&lt;/a&gt;, but my decision largely came down to favoring an unrestricted, open-source solution. I&amp;rsquo;m definitely not a seasoned practitioner, so it&amp;rsquo;s unlikely that I would really be able to appreciate the difference between the two products right now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;network&#34;&gt;Network&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start with, having some virtual machines running on an internal network, isolated from the home network by a firewall, sounds like a good idea. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.pfsense.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;pfSense&lt;/a&gt; is a well-regarded firewall whose documentation specifically includes guidance on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.netgate.com/pfsense/en/latest/virtualization/virtualizing-pfsense-with-proxmox.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;running it as a VM in Proxmox&lt;/a&gt;, which is exactly what I want to do. It also can be configured as an intrusion detection/prevention system by way of add-on packages like Suricata and Snort, something I&amp;rsquo;m keen to play around with in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although I&amp;rsquo;m generally comfortable with vanilla home networking, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of uncharted territory for me in this project. To limit what could go wrong, I will keep things simple and just focus on getting a basic system up-and-running. This means leaving things like VLAN configuration and SSH access for another homelab iteration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The schematic for the eventual homelab is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-1b-homelab-schematic-with-two-virtual-switches-vmbrx-and-three-vms&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/homelab/network-diagram.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 1&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. Homelab schematic, with two virtual switches (&amp;lt;code&amp;gt;vmbrx&amp;lt;/code&amp;gt;) and three VMs.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/homelab/network-diagram.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 1&lt;/b&gt;. Homelab schematic, with two virtual switches (&lt;code&gt;vmbrx&lt;/code&gt;) and three VMs.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;installation&#34;&gt;Installation&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before beginning, you should have the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\geq$8 GB USB flash drive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rufus installer (&lt;code&gt;rufus-3.10.exe&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proxmox VE ISO image (&lt;code&gt;proxmox-ve_6.2-1.iso&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pfSense ISO image (&lt;code&gt;pfSense-CE-2.4.5-RELEASE-amd64.iso&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Linux ISO image (&lt;code&gt;CentOS-8.1.1911-x86_64-dvd1.iso&lt;/code&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://rufus.ie/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Rufus&lt;/a&gt; will be used to wipe and format the USB drive as a bootable installation drive&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, so please make sure it&amp;rsquo;s not holding anything of value! Once you&amp;rsquo;ve selected the USB drive under &lt;em&gt;Device&lt;/em&gt; and the Proxmox ISO image under &lt;em&gt;Boot selection&lt;/em&gt;, go ahead and click Start. You might get a couple of prompts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Download a newer version of GRUB?&amp;rdquo; → &lt;strong&gt;No&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Write as an ISO image or DD image?&amp;rdquo; → &lt;strong&gt;Write in DD Image mode&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the disk is written, plug it into your homelab host and turn it on. Immediately hold down ESC or DEL and let go once you&amp;rsquo;ve entered the BIOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    At this point, you should probably enable &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unified_Extensible_Firmware_Interface&#34;&gt;UEFI&lt;/a&gt; mode. Most operating systems these days support UEFI, which allows for things like using a mouse in the installation GUI. The only reason to use legacy mode is for compatibility with ancient OS installation media.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    While we&amp;rsquo;re here, make sure that the relevant virtualization setting (Intel VT, AMD-V, SVM, etc) is enabled.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within the BIOS, find the boot section and either reorder the device list such that your USB drive comes first, or if there&amp;rsquo;s an option to immediately boot from a selected device, use that to boot from the drive. Selecting &lt;strong&gt;Install Proxmox VE&lt;/strong&gt; from the menu that pops up will launch the installatoon process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;installing-proxmox&#34;&gt;Installing Proxmox&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While going through the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://pve.proxmox.com/wiki/Installation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;installation process&lt;/a&gt;, you will have to make some important decisions. The first of these concerns what file system to use on the host.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;file-system&#34;&gt;File system&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we ignore Ext3, we have three choices: Ext4, XFS, and ZFS. The default file system, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://opensource.com/article/18/4/ext4-filesystem&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ext4&lt;/a&gt;, was designed to be backwards-compatible with older file systems. It&amp;rsquo;s known for stability, which is probably the reason why it&amp;rsquo;s the default file system on most Linux distributions. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.usenix.org/system/files/login/articles/140-hellwig.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;XFS&lt;/a&gt; is another mature solution that is particularly well-suited for servers that deal with many large (exbibytes) files.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.freebsd.org/doc/handbook/zfs.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ZFS&lt;/a&gt; is a next-generation file system that was designed to eliminate many issues found in legacy file systems. ZFS is probably the way to go for someone who knows what they&amp;rsquo;re doing (and doesn&amp;rsquo;t need support for enormous files) &amp;ndash; you get great performance, configuration flexibility, and access to enterprise-level features, in return for a larger memory footprint and a bit more configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since I&amp;rsquo;m just learning the ropes and don&amp;rsquo;t really need advanced features and capabilities, I left Proxmox with Ext4 as the default choice. You would only see the option to change this by clicking &lt;em&gt;Options&lt;/em&gt; next to the Target Harddisk dropdown during the installation, so keep this in mind if you want to choose a different file system&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;network-configuration&#34;&gt;Network configuration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proxmox will eventually ask you to confirm your network configuration. The IP address here will be accessed by a browser on another computer on your network, allowing you to perform hypervisor management through a web interface. Choose an IP address that is on the same network segment as your router (and home network). If your router is running DHCP, you want this management address to be outside of the DHCP pool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve selected &lt;code&gt;192.168.0.10/24&lt;/code&gt; as the management IP address, with the address of my router (&lt;code&gt;192.168.0.1&lt;/code&gt;) as the gateway. Keep the management address handy. I&amp;rsquo;ve also gone with a FQDN (fully-qualified domain name) of &lt;code&gt;pve.alex.home&lt;/code&gt;, which implies the hostname &lt;code&gt;pve&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    If you want to change the management IP address later, you will need to do it in &lt;em&gt;two&lt;/em&gt; places: (a) &lt;code&gt;/etc/hosts&lt;/code&gt; and (b) &lt;code&gt;/etc/network/interfaces&lt;/code&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ll look at the latter configuration file later on.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;configuring-proxmox&#34;&gt;Configuring Proxmox&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the installation has finished, remove the USB drive and reboot. You&amp;rsquo;ll eventually see a prompt that asks you to configure Proxmox by visiting &lt;code&gt;https://&amp;lt;MANAGEMENT-IP&amp;gt;:8006&lt;/code&gt;. Provided you&amp;rsquo;ve configured the network settings properly, you will be able to access the web GUI from another computer in your home network by entering that address in a browser. Once you&amp;rsquo;ve supplied your credentials (user &lt;code&gt;root&lt;/code&gt; and the password you specified earlier) and logged in, you are ready to start configuring the hypervisor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;enabling-software-updates&#34;&gt;Enabling software updates&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, it&amp;rsquo;s a good idea to enable software updates. Proxmox is configured by default to access the software repositories for subscribed customers, which are not accessible to those without a subscription. We&amp;rsquo;re going to configure Proxmox to access the community repositories instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s take a quick look at the interface. On the left you&amp;rsquo;ve got the &lt;em&gt;resource tree&lt;/em&gt;, a column that gives you an overview of your hypervisor (Fig. 2, left column). Underneath &lt;em&gt;Datacenter&lt;/em&gt;, you&amp;rsquo;ve got a single &lt;em&gt;node&lt;/em&gt; with hostname &lt;code&gt;pve&lt;/code&gt;. One more level down lists all the VMs and logical storage devices associated with the node. At the moment there are no VMs and two shared storage objects called &lt;code&gt;local&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;local-lvm&lt;/code&gt; that resulted from the default Proxmox installation options. The &lt;code&gt;local-lvm&lt;/code&gt; object holds VM disk images, while the &lt;code&gt;local&lt;/code&gt; object holds backup files and ISO images. We&amp;rsquo;ll be dealing with &lt;code&gt;local&lt;/code&gt; shortly.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-2b-left-column-proxmox-resource-tree-showing-the-vms-and-storage-objects-available-to-the-node-pve-right-panel-iso-images-in-local-shared-storage-after-uploading-to-the-host&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/homelab/proxmox-storage.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 2&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. Left column: Proxmox resource tree, showing the VMs and storage objects available to the node &amp;lt;code&amp;gt;pve&amp;lt;/code&amp;gt;. Right panel: ISO images in &amp;lt;code&amp;gt;local&amp;lt;/code&amp;gt; shared storage after uploading to the host.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/homelab/proxmox-storage.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 2&lt;/b&gt;. Left column: Proxmox resource tree, showing the VMs and storage objects available to the node &lt;code&gt;pve&lt;/code&gt;. Right panel: ISO images in &lt;code&gt;local&lt;/code&gt; shared storage after uploading to the host.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The toolbar in Fig. 2 above (with title &lt;em&gt;Storage &amp;lsquo;local&amp;rsquo; on node &amp;lsquo;pve&amp;rsquo;&lt;/em&gt; and button &lt;em&gt;Help&lt;/em&gt; on the right) will change according to the selected resource in the tree. Clicking the &lt;code&gt;pve&lt;/code&gt; node will bring up node-specific toolbar buttons, like &lt;em&gt;Reboot&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Shutdown&lt;/em&gt;, and &lt;em&gt;Shell&lt;/em&gt;. Go ahead and click that &lt;strong&gt;Shell&lt;/strong&gt; button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to configure the software repositories. Debian (Proxmox&amp;rsquo;s underlying operating system) makes use of &lt;code&gt;apt&lt;/code&gt; (Advanced Package Tool) to manage and update software. We are going to navigate to the directory that holds the repository configuration, rename (and effectively disable) the config file, and create a new config file containing a link to the community repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;cd /etc/apt/sources.list.d
mv pve-enterprise.list pve-enterprise.list.original
echo &#39;deb http://download.proxmox.com/debian/pve buster pve-no-subscription&#39; &amp;gt; pve-community.list
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    &lt;code&gt;buster&lt;/code&gt; is the name of the Debian release used by Proxmox 6. Make sure to use the release name for your version of Proxmox.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can now run &lt;code&gt;apt update&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;apt dist-upgrade&lt;/code&gt; to download and install all available updates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;uploading-iso-images&#34;&gt;Uploading ISO images&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we can start making VMs, we need to upload the ISO installation media. Click the &lt;code&gt;local&lt;/code&gt; storage object &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Content&lt;/em&gt; tab to bring up a (currently empty) list of items sitting in the storage. After using the Upload button to store the pfSense and CentOS ISO images, the list will look like Fig. 2 (right panel).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;configuring-the-virtual-network&#34;&gt;Configuring the virtual network&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned earlier, the host will have two network segments: one that allows the host to communicate with the home network, and an internal network segment, insulated by a firewall. This section talks about the configuration needed to prepare the virtualized network for the firewall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;virtual-switches&#34;&gt;Virtual switches&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The network components available to Proxmox can be found by clicking the &lt;code&gt;pve&lt;/code&gt; node &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;System&lt;/em&gt; tab group &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Network&lt;/em&gt; tab. The Protectli box has six NICs, which are listed as &lt;code&gt;enp[1-6]s0&lt;/code&gt; in Fig. 3 below as Network Devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll also see something called a &lt;em&gt;Linux Bridge&lt;/em&gt;, named &lt;code&gt;vmbr0&lt;/code&gt;. This behaves like a network switch, allowing for communication between devices using both virtual and physical interfaces. Currently it&amp;rsquo;s associated with one physical interface (&lt;code&gt;enp1s0&lt;/code&gt;), through which the host is connected to the router. The bridge is also associated with Proxmox through its management IP address (&lt;code&gt;192.168.0.10/24&lt;/code&gt;). If we connected a VM to &lt;code&gt;vmbr0&lt;/code&gt; and gave it an IP address from the same subnet, that VM will gain access to both Proxmox&amp;rsquo;s management interface and the router. We&amp;rsquo;ll be doing exactly this for pfSense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    A Linux Bridge &lt;a href=&#34;https://unix.stackexchange.com/questions/572261/virtual-network-bridge-why-does-it-have-to-have-an-ip-address-assigned-to-it&#34;&gt;does not necessarily need an IP address&lt;/a&gt;, but since we want to be able to manage Proxmox from the home network, we need &lt;code&gt;vmbr0&lt;/code&gt; to be bound to an IP address on the home network subnet, &lt;code&gt;192.168.0.0/24&lt;/code&gt;.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-3b-proxmox-network-devices-shown-with-two-linux-bridges&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/homelab/proxmox-network.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 3&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. Proxmox network devices, shown with two Linux Bridges.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/homelab/proxmox-network.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 3&lt;/b&gt;. Proxmox network devices, shown with two Linux Bridges.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;forwarding-between-private-networks&#34;&gt;Forwarding between (private) networks&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we&amp;rsquo;re going to focus on the internal network segment, which needs its own Linux Bridge. Make one and call it &lt;code&gt;vmbr1&lt;/code&gt;, without assigning an IP address or any other settings to the bridge. The internal network will make use of the subnet &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.0/24&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As useful as Proxmox&amp;rsquo;s web interface is, we cannot use it to completely configure the virtual network for our use case. To make this work, we need to directly edit the &lt;code&gt;/etc/network/interfaces&lt;/code&gt; file to ask Proxmox to do two things for us:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;forward IP packets across different network segments, and&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_address_translation&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;IP masquerading&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The effect of (2) will be to allow all devices in the internal network (each with their own private IP address on the internal subnet) to communicate with the outside world using a single &amp;ldquo;external&amp;rdquo; IP address &amp;ndash; the address of the host.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    I say &amp;ldquo;external&amp;rdquo; in quotes because often when we talk about NAT (network address translation), we&amp;rsquo;re mapping a private IP address to a &lt;em&gt;public&lt;/em&gt; IP address. Here we&amp;rsquo;re mapping private IP addresses to another private IP address.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we take a look at &lt;code&gt;/etc/network/interfaces&lt;/code&gt;, we will see the six physical interfaces, &lt;code&gt;enp[1-6]s0&lt;/code&gt;, as well as &lt;code&gt;vmbr0&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;vmbr1&lt;/code&gt;. The configuration for the two Linux Bridges is shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;auto vmbr0
iface vmbr0 inet static
        address 192.168.0.10/24
        gateway 192.168.0.1
        bridge-ports enp1s0
        bridge-stp off
        bridge-fd 0

auto vmbr1
iface vmbr1 inet manual
        bridge-ports none
        bridge-stp off
        bridge-fd 0
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can confirm that only &lt;code&gt;vmbr0&lt;/code&gt; has an IP address and gateway, allowing for communication between the host, router, and firewall on the &lt;code&gt;192.168.0.0/24&lt;/code&gt; subnet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the file, we will add the following three lines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;post-up echo 1 &amp;gt; /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward
post-up iptables -t nat -A POSTROUTING -s &#39;192.168.1.0/24&#39; -o vmbr0 -j MASQUERADE
post-down iptables -t nat -D POSTROUTING -s &#39;192.168.1.0/24&#39; -o vmbr0 -j MASQUERADE
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first line enables packet forwarding after the interface has been brought up, and the next two lines conditionally add/remove a rule for 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://linux.die.net/man/8/iptables&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Proxmox&amp;rsquo;s firewall&lt;/a&gt;. Let&amp;rsquo;s break it down:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-t nat -A POSTROUTING&lt;/code&gt;: the rule gets added to the POSTROUTING NAT table, to alter packets as they leave the interface,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-s &#39;192.168.1.0/24&#39;&lt;/code&gt;: the rule applies to any packet whose source IP belongs to the internal network,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-o vmbr0&lt;/code&gt;: matching packets get sent to interface &lt;code&gt;vmbr0&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;-j MASQUERADE&lt;/code&gt;: matching packets get their source IP replaced by that of &lt;code&gt;vmbr0&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the last line, instead of adding the rule after the interface is brought up, the rule is removed after the interface is brought down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize, the effect of this extra configuration is to take packets that are heading out from the internal network (e.g. with source IP &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.99&lt;/code&gt;), replace their source IPs with &lt;code&gt;192.168.0.10&lt;/code&gt;, and send them on their way. When an internal VM&amp;rsquo;s network request is reciprocated by a public server, the server will send packets that are addressed to Proxmox, which will intercept and redirect those packets back through the firewall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;installing-pfsense&#34;&gt;Installing pfSense&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are finally ready to create our pfSense virtual machine! In this homelab iteration, the firewall is just going to have a small amount of configuration to control administrative access and configure DHCP to assign IP addresses to two CentOS VMs (a client and a server) using their MAC addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since there&amp;rsquo;s not going to be any heavy traffic processing going on here, I&amp;rsquo;ve opted for a single-core VM (hostname &lt;code&gt;pfsense&lt;/code&gt;) with pfSense&amp;rsquo;s minimum hardware requirements (512 MiB RAM and 4 GiB of disk space), using the Create Virtual Machine dialog to choose a VirtIO SCSI controller and VirtIO network device connected to the &lt;code&gt;vmbr0&lt;/code&gt; bridge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    According to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://pve.proxmox.com/wiki/Qemu/KVM_Virtual_Machines&#34;&gt;documentation&lt;/a&gt;, we should use paravirtualized (VirtIO) devices where possible. Paravirtualization allows guest operating systems to talk directly to the hypervisor, which generally leads to improved performance and less virtualization overhead.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we&amp;rsquo;ll add another network device to the VM. In the resource tree, click the &lt;code&gt;pfsense&lt;/code&gt; VM &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hardware&lt;/em&gt; tab &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Add&lt;/em&gt; dropdown button &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Network Device&lt;/em&gt;, to connect &lt;code&gt;vmbr1&lt;/code&gt;. Now the pfSense VM has two NICs: &lt;code&gt;net0&lt;/code&gt;, connected to &lt;code&gt;vmbr0&lt;/code&gt;, and &lt;code&gt;net1&lt;/code&gt;, connected to &lt;code&gt;vmbr1&lt;/code&gt;. Start up the VM and install pfSense with all of the defaults.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;configuring-pfsense&#34;&gt;Configuring pfSense&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After installation and a reboot, pfSense will ask whether you want to set up VLANs. We&amp;rsquo;re not doing this, but before you proceed, make sure you see two valid interfaces, &lt;code&gt;vtnet0&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;vtnet1&lt;/code&gt;, listed above the prompt. Next, you&amp;rsquo;ll get a couple more prompts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Enter the WAN interface name&amp;rdquo; → &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;vtnetx&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;Enter the LAN interface name&amp;rdquo; → &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;vtnety&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Make sure that each interface corresponds to its Linux Bridge counterpart (e.g. &lt;code&gt;vtnet0&lt;/code&gt; is &lt;code&gt;vmbr0&lt;/code&gt;). Check that the listed MAC addresses match the ones found under &lt;em&gt;Datacenter&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;code&gt;pve&lt;/code&gt; node &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;code&gt;pfSense&lt;/code&gt; VM &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hardware&lt;/em&gt; tab.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The WAN interface is the firewall&amp;rsquo;s untrusted entrance. If I were confident that these homelab shenanigans wouldn&amp;rsquo;t eventually disrupt my internet connectivity, I&amp;rsquo;d arrange for the firewall to handle internet traffic directly, before forwarding traffic to the home router and network through the firewall&amp;rsquo;s LAN interface. (But I&amp;rsquo;m not. At least, not yet!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After confirming the above information, pfSense will continue booting and eventually present you with a menu (Fig. 3). In my case, the router has allocated pfSense&amp;rsquo;s WAN interface an IP address, &lt;code&gt;192.168.0.180/24&lt;/code&gt;. That is a nice gesture, but I want to give it a static IP address. After choosing option 2, enter the WAN&amp;rsquo;s new IP address as &lt;code&gt;192.168.0.11/24&lt;/code&gt; and a gateway of &lt;code&gt;192.168.0.1&lt;/code&gt;. Enter &lt;strong&gt;no&lt;/strong&gt; when asked to revert to HTTP as the webConfigurator protocol (this is unimportant right now). Time to reboot.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-3b-pfsense-command-line-menu&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/homelab/pfsense-menu.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 3&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. pfSense command line menu.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/homelab/pfsense-menu.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 3&lt;/b&gt;. pfSense command line menu.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;using-the-setup-wizard&#34;&gt;Using the setup wizard&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we&amp;rsquo;re back at the menu, we can access the management GUI using the WAN interface IP address, although we need to temporarily disable the firewall to access it. Choose option 8 to enter the shell, run &lt;code&gt;pfctl -d&lt;/code&gt; to bring down the firewall, and then enter &lt;code&gt;192.168.0.11&lt;/code&gt; in a browser on your home network. After supplying the default credentials (username &lt;code&gt;admin&lt;/code&gt;, password &lt;code&gt;pfsense&lt;/code&gt;), you&amp;rsquo;ll be brought to pfSense&amp;rsquo;s setup wizard. I&amp;rsquo;ll highlight some important configuration below (with the steps in parentheses):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(2/9)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hostname/domain&lt;/em&gt;: nice to make these match your Proxmox details,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(2/9)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Primary/secondary&lt;/em&gt; DNS Server: as above,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(3/9)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Timezone&lt;/em&gt;: choose yours,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(4/9)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Static IP configuration&lt;/em&gt;: make sure these details are correct (&lt;code&gt;192.168.0.11/24&lt;/code&gt;, with gateway &lt;code&gt;192.168.0.1&lt;/code&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(4/9)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;RFC1918/bogon networks&lt;/em&gt;: uncheck the two boxes to allow private/non-internet routed networks through the WAN interface &amp;ndash; this firewall will of course be dealing with these kinds of networks,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(5/9)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Configure LAN interface&lt;/em&gt;: make sure these details are correct (&lt;code&gt;192.168.1.1/24&lt;/code&gt;) &amp;ndash; this will be the gateway for the VMs in the internal network,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(6/9)&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Set admin webGUI password&lt;/em&gt;: now&amp;rsquo;s a good time!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting the admin password will trigger an update, after which you will get kicked off the management GUI. Go ahead and reboot the pfSense VM. We haven&amp;rsquo;t yet made allowances for management access in the firewall, so once it&amp;rsquo;s ready you will have to once again disable the firewall (&lt;code&gt;pfctl -d&lt;/code&gt;) before logging back in with your new credentials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;playing-nice-with-virtio&#34;&gt;Playing nice with VirtIO&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you try moving through different parts of the web interface, you might notice that it seems a bit sluggish. This comes about from an issue with using VirtIO network drivers to interface with pfSense, which can be resolved by changing a couple of settings as recommended by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.netgate.com/pfsense/en/latest/virtualization/virtualizing-pfsense-with-proxmox.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;the documentation&lt;/a&gt; (section &lt;em&gt;Configuring pfSense Software to work with Proxmox VirtIO&lt;/em&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click the &lt;em&gt;System&lt;/em&gt; header menu &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Advanced&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Networking&lt;/em&gt; tab and scroll to the bottom to the &lt;em&gt;Network Interfaces&lt;/em&gt; section. Make sure these boxes below are checked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Disable hardware checksum offload&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Disable hardware TCP segmentation offload&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;input checked=&#34;&#34; disabled=&#34;&#34; type=&#34;checkbox&#34;&gt; Disable hardware large receive offload&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;allowing-administrative-access&#34;&gt;Allowing administrative access&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our next order of business is to allow ourselves administrative access, so that we don&amp;rsquo;t have to tear down our firewall every time we need to perform some management. We are going to do a couple of things here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;define &lt;em&gt;aliases&lt;/em&gt; to specify IP management ports,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use these aliases to allow pfSense management through those ports.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To define the aliases, click the &lt;em&gt;Firewall&lt;/em&gt; header menu &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Aliases&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Ports&lt;/em&gt; tab, and then click &lt;em&gt;Add&lt;/em&gt;. We will allow management through ports 80 (HTTP) and 8080 (alt-HTTP). When you&amp;rsquo;ve got these ports listed as in Fig. 4 below, save and apply the changes when prompted.&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-4b-specifying-pfsense-aliases&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/homelab/pfsense-aliases.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 4&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. Specifying pfSense aliases.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/homelab/pfsense-aliases.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 4&lt;/b&gt;. Specifying pfSense aliases.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we will add a rule to allow management traffic through the WAN interface. The rule we add will act on inbound packets at the interface. Click the &lt;em&gt;Firewall&lt;/em&gt; header menu &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Rules&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;WAN&lt;/em&gt; tab, and then click &lt;em&gt;Add&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stepping through the configuration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Edit firewall rule&lt;/em&gt;: pass TCP IPv4 traffic through the WAN interface &amp;ndash; you will find that the default settings under this heading work for us,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Source&lt;/em&gt;: allow access to home network devices, so specify &lt;em&gt;Network&lt;/em&gt; and enter &lt;code&gt;192.168.0.0/24&lt;/code&gt;,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Destination&lt;/em&gt;: match traffic headed for this firewall (select this in the destination dropdown) through the management ports (fill out the &lt;em&gt;Custom&lt;/em&gt; port ranges with the alias &lt;code&gt;pfsense_admin_ports&lt;/code&gt;),&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Extra options&lt;/em&gt;: fill out the description with something like &amp;ldquo;allow administrative access from home network&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After saving the new firewall rule, we will get pfSense to provide access to the management interface through the alternative HTTP port. Click the &lt;em&gt;System&lt;/em&gt; header menu &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Advanced&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Admin Access&lt;/em&gt; tab, enter &lt;code&gt;8080&lt;/code&gt; in the &lt;em&gt;TCP port&lt;/em&gt; field, and apply the changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    A firewall will go through each of its rules until it finds a match, at which point it will act on the traffic according to the matching rule. If an inbound packet doesn&amp;rsquo;t match any rule, the packet gets dropped.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.w3.org/Daemon/User/Installation/PrivilegedPorts.html&#34;&gt;good practice&lt;/a&gt; to serve the web interface on alternative HTTP port &lt;code&gt;8080&lt;/code&gt;, as some systems require full administrative privileges to access port numbers lower than &lt;code&gt;1024&lt;/code&gt; (like the HTTP port &lt;code&gt;80&lt;/code&gt;, for example).
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can freely manage the firewall through the web interface! You can either reboot the router or run &lt;code&gt;pfctrl -e&lt;/code&gt; to bring the firewall back online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-the-internal-network&#34;&gt;Creating the internal network&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re now going to create two CentOS VMs: a client VM and server VM. In reality they will be pretty much identical (save for their NIC MAC addresses) but they will play certain roles as I learn the ropes of system administration. I will then configure pfSense to assign each VM with an IP address that allows them to communicate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up a CentOS VM is pretty straightforward. The first one will have the hostname &lt;code&gt;centos-server&lt;/code&gt;. It will have 1 CPU, 2 GiB RAM, 20 GiB of hard disk space, and be connected to &lt;code&gt;vmbr1&lt;/code&gt;. Here we will choose a &lt;em&gt;non-paravirtualized&lt;/em&gt; NIC model, the Intel E1000.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-warning&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    Make sure you &lt;strong&gt;do not&lt;/strong&gt; choose the VirtIO network device! With that NIC, I could &lt;code&gt;ping google.com&lt;/code&gt; but could not &lt;code&gt;curl google.com&lt;/code&gt;. This was the cause of hours of madness, until &lt;a href=&#34;https://forum.netgate.com/topic/79004/pfsense-2-2-not-passing-traffic-but-ping-does-get-through/23&#34;&gt;this forum post&lt;/a&gt; gave me a hint. There is apparently an issue with a VM using paravirtualized network drivers to communicate with pfSense, but it&amp;rsquo;s not at all clear why.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;rsquo;ve run through the installation and logged in, you should be able to access the internet through the VM (provided you&amp;rsquo;ve got a working DNS configuration). Now the VM can be cloned to yield &lt;code&gt;centos-client&lt;/code&gt; and there will be two functional VMs on the internal network, with full internet connectivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;restricting-access&#34;&gt;Restricting access&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re pretty close to achieving the design goal. The main issue is that right now, the firewall isn&amp;rsquo;t really doing much. Now I want to restrict access to whitelist these two CentOS VMs and nothing more. To do this, I&amp;rsquo;ll make use of pfSense&amp;rsquo;s DHCP service to map each MAC address to a static IP address on the internal network segment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;mapping-vms-to-ip-addresses&#34;&gt;Mapping VMs to IP addresses&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The MAC address of a given VM can be accessed by selecting the VM in the Proxmox resource tree &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Hardware&lt;/em&gt; tab and double-clicking the &lt;em&gt;Network Device&lt;/em&gt; row associated with &lt;code&gt;vmbr1&lt;/code&gt;. Grab the server and client MAC addresses and keep them handy. Incidentally, I&amp;rsquo;ll be assigning &lt;code&gt;centos-server&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.101&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;centos-client&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.102&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s head back into the pfSense web interface and click the &lt;em&gt;Services&lt;/em&gt; header menu &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;DHCP Server&lt;/em&gt;. At the moment, the VMs are getting their IP addresses from the available range indicated at the bottom of the &lt;em&gt;General Options&lt;/em&gt; section. Set the range to &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.220&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.240&lt;/code&gt; and click &lt;strong&gt;Save&lt;/strong&gt;. The specific range isn&amp;rsquo;t too important &amp;ndash; we just want the range not to include any of the static VM addresses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the bottom of the page there&amp;rsquo;s a section called &lt;em&gt;DHCP Static Mappings for this Interface&lt;/em&gt;, which sounds like what we want. Click &lt;strong&gt;Add&lt;/strong&gt; to add a mapping for both VMs, filling out the MAC address, client identifier, IP address, and hostname for each mapping (Fig. 5).&lt;/p&gt;















&lt;figure id=&#34;figure-bfig-5b-specifying-dhcp-static-mappings-for-the-centos-vms&#34;&gt;


  &lt;a data-fancybox=&#34;&#34; href=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/homelab/pfsense-mappings.png&#34; data-caption=&#34;&amp;lt;b&amp;gt;Fig. 5&amp;lt;/b&amp;gt;. Specifying DHCP static mappings for the CentOS VMs.&#34;&gt;


  &lt;img src=&#34;https://www.remotelycurious.net/homelab/pfsense-mappings.png&#34; alt=&#34;&#34;  &gt;
&lt;/a&gt;


  
  
  &lt;figcaption&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Fig. 5&lt;/b&gt;. Specifying DHCP static mappings for the CentOS VMs.
  &lt;/figcaption&gt;


&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can now bring a VM&amp;rsquo;s interface down and back up again to reassign the IP address, confirming the change with the last command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;nmcli connection down ens18
nmcli connection up ens18
ip address show ens18
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;blacklisting-unknown-devices&#34;&gt;Blacklisting unknown devices&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our final act, we are going to block traffic leaving the internal network from all unauthorized devices, i.e., anything other than &lt;code&gt;centos-server&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;centos-client&lt;/code&gt;. This can be done by whitelisting the network &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.100/30&lt;/code&gt; and blocking everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the pfSense interface, click the &lt;em&gt;Firewall&lt;/em&gt; header menu &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;Rules&lt;/em&gt; &lt;i class=&#34;fas fa-angle-double-right&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt; &lt;em&gt;LAN&lt;/em&gt; tab. We will create a rule to pass IPv4 packets from &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; protocol with a source IP coming from the network &lt;code&gt;192.168.1.100/30&lt;/code&gt;. After disabling any other rules and applying the changes, we have successfully locked down the internal network. You can confirm this by manually setting one of the VM&amp;rsquo;s IP addresses to a non-whitelisted address and running &lt;code&gt;curl google.com&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At last, the homelab is up and running! There is of course a lot that can be done to improve this setup, particularly in the way of security. I think it would be a great idea to configure VLANs and enable SSH access for firewall management in the next homelab iteration, but for now it can serve as a testbed for all sorts of administrative tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;section class=&#34;footnotes&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnotes&#34;&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another solution would be to implement the lab on a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://cloud.google.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;cloud platform&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cross-platform alternative to Rufus is 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.balena.io/etcher/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Etcher&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34; role=&#34;doc-endnote&#34;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://access.redhat.com/articles/3129891&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; from Red Hat for a good discussion about how to choose a file system (although they conspicuously do not mention ZFS).&amp;#160;&lt;a href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34; class=&#34;footnote-backref&#34; role=&#34;doc-backlink&#34;&gt;&amp;#x21a9;&amp;#xfe0e;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/section&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
